<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>HookFeed Blog</title>
  <id>http://www.hookfeed.com/blog</id>
  <link href="http://www.hookfeed.com/blog"/>
  <link href="http://www.hookfeed.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2014-05-14T07:00:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Matt Goldman</name>
    <name>Joelle Steiniger</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>When Profitability is a Red Flag</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.hookfeed.com/blog/when-profitability-is-a-red-flag/"/>
    <id>http://www.hookfeed.com/blog/when-profitability-is-a-red-flag/</id>
    <published>2014-05-14T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-06-04T01:34:05-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Matt Goldman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="When Profitability is a Red Flag" src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/HookFeed/profitability_blog_header.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;When Profitability is a Red Flag&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Or, The Difference Between a Business and a Startup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have a business degree. I do have entrepreneurial parents. My father has a commercial real estate development company with a number of employees. My mother is a Dietician running a solo private practice. Their businesses are completely different in almost every way, except for one: profitability is the main goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what I grew up knowing about business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href="http://howtobuildarocketship.com/podcast/ep-27-jason-cohen/"&gt;recent interview&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/asmartbear"&gt;Jason Cohen&lt;/a&gt;, Founder of &lt;a href="http://wpengine.com"&gt;WP Engine&lt;/a&gt;, we got to talking about business goals. He said something that, at the time, seemed jarring to me, though I’ve since come to understand his point. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Profitability is the last thing you want. Profitability indicates you’re out of ideas.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What he means is:&lt;/strong&gt; If you had ideas of how to continue to grow, you’d invest back into the company to pursue those avenues, and grow until the seams burst (or you IPO ☺). Then you grow some more. You wouldn’t kick back in your Herman Miller chair and brag to your investors about the massive profits you’re piling up (you’d probably scare the crap out of them).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jason Cohen is running a startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;So what’s the difference between a Business and a Startup?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trick question - they’re both businesses. The difference is their objectives. And the difference in objectives means big differences in how they operate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Businesses&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; are, in fact, driven by profitability and stable long-term value. Sure, you’ll invest some portion of profits back into the company to continue to grow at a stable rate, but profitability is still your north star. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Startups&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; on the other hand, are focused on top-end revenue, but most importantly, &lt;strong&gt;growth potential&lt;/strong&gt;. Growth trumps profitability, which is why most VC backed startups are operating at seemingly huge losses. It’s an investment in &lt;em&gt;growth potential&lt;/em&gt;, and this is a very different kind of business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which one is better? That’s like asking if chocolate or vanilla is better. It all depends on what you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Steve Blank shares his fantastic perspective in this short 2 minute video:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/CIA9ikESXYI" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I guess the reason Jason’s comment took me a little while to process is because it went against everything I knew (at that point in time) about running a business. (I still have a lot to learn).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Profitability has always been my bottom-line goal (and still is) for my product &lt;a href="http://hookfeed.com"&gt;HookFeed&lt;/a&gt;. Yet, if you ask me to describe what I do, the word ‘startup’ is one of the first words out of my mouth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is HookFeed? Is it a startup, or a business? Or, rather, a better question might be: what do I want it to be? Because the answer to that would (and should) drastically change the things I work on (and towards) today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re in a similar boat, trying to figure out what you are or what you want to be, I’ll leave you with this: there’s a reason the rate of failure for startups is so high. It’s the same reason the payoff for success is also high. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s a risk : reward ratio.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while figuring out your risk tolerance is important, and will certainly help guide you in the right direction in a practical sense, it should only be a piece of your evaluation. Ultimately, it comes down to asking yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; idea of success? What will make &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; happy?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you can answer that, you’ll know what to work on today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, I can’t help but think of myself at the frozen yogurt shop faced with the cliché choice of chocolate or vanilla. I’m a swirl kinda girl… maybe that’s a sign?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Don't Blow Your Opportunity to Squash Customer Objections</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.hookfeed.com/blog/dont-blow-your-opportunity-to-squash-customer-objections/"/>
    <id>http://www.hookfeed.com/blog/dont-blow-your-opportunity-to-squash-customer-objections/</id>
    <published>2014-04-07T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-04-07T08:59:12-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Matt Goldman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/smallhq/big-vs-small.gif" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t Blow Your Opportunity to Squash Customer Objections&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I was 18 and on my way downtown to start my first company.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many aspects were uncertain, but one thing was for sure: the name had to sound legit. If I wanted my company to be successful like the ones on TV, people would need to think it was huge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So naturally, I took my initials, added some awesome, and ended up with &lt;strong&gt;MHG Enterprises&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did everything right. I started with business cards, a fancy title, a &amp;ldquo;business&amp;rdquo; phone number &lt;em&gt;(my parent&amp;rsquo;s home phone)&lt;/em&gt;, address labels, printed envelopes&amp;hellip;the whole shebang!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Except I did everything wrong.&lt;/strong&gt; People love working with small companies&amp;hellip;as long as they have strong faith that you&amp;rsquo;re capable of delivering on your promises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past few years, I&amp;rsquo;ve drifted towards the other end of the spectrum naming my current company &lt;a href="http://smallhq.com?utm_source=hookfeed_blog&amp;amp;utm_medium=blog&amp;amp;utm_campaign=dont-act-big-dont-act-small"&gt;Small HQ&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s no secret that we are small &lt;em&gt;(just &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SDMattG"&gt;me&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/JoelleSteiniger"&gt;Joelle&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;, and that we want to stay small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it wasn&amp;rsquo;t until recently that we realized the negative effects this was having on our product, &lt;a href="http://hookfeed.com?utm_source=hookfeed_blog&amp;amp;utm_medium=blog&amp;amp;utm_campaign=dont-act-big-dont-act-small"&gt;HookFeed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without even thinking twice about it, we took the pride of being small and injected it directly into HookFeed&amp;rsquo;s sign up page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/smallhq/old-vs-new-signup.gif" alt="Old vs. New HookFeed sign up Pages" class="full-image"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Old Page&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn&amp;rsquo;t our first rodeo - we&amp;rsquo;d been building and supporting products for about a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One realization we&amp;rsquo;d made was that a personal touch could go a long way. It&amp;rsquo;s one of the (many) reasons why we use &lt;a href="https://www.intercom.io/"&gt;Intercom&lt;/a&gt; to communicate with our customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love when, as the customer of another product, the founder reaches out to help me. It shows that they are small enough to be the sort of company I&amp;rsquo;d like to work with, and serious enough that the founder sees the value in going the extra mile for customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Joelle and I let this personalization go a bit too far when designing our page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;HookFeed is 100% founder-funded and made with love in sunny San Diego&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Mostly selfish reasons. What does our funding or location have to do with what our potential customers are thinking when they sign up? &lt;strong&gt;Not-a-damn-thing!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to mention the form was so tall that it pushed the section off the page for most visitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The New Page&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After taking a second look many weeks later &lt;em&gt;(with a clear mind)&lt;/em&gt;, we decided to remove the section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It made us seem like too small of a team to take seriously, and didn&amp;rsquo;t accomplish the original goal: showing that we&amp;rsquo;re here, and ready to hustle for whatever you need as our customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;A Personal Touch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wanted to keep a personal photo of one of us, and offer to help with any questions they may have. We really are just an email away, and that sets us apart from a large, faceless company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Joelle Offering Help to New Customers" src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/smallhq/joelle-help-box.gif" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new help box is featured prominently, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t give the impression that the company is tiny, unlike the first version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Objection Squashing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you&amp;rsquo;re a small team running a big product&amp;hellip;it&amp;rsquo;s easy to get a page to &amp;ldquo;Done&amp;rdquo; and then move on to more important matters for weeks or months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of our sign up page, we launched with two objection-squashing Q&amp;amp;As right next to the credit card form (inspired by &lt;a href="https://secure.letsfreckle.com/signup/Small"&gt;Freckle&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; sign up page).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time of launch, we didn&amp;rsquo;t have a free plan, so the Q&amp;amp;As were focused on the concerns of paying users. In the rush to update our pricing structure&amp;hellip;we forgot to update our sign up page with more appropriate objection-busters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that if I were signing up for a free plan, I would not expect to need to give a credit card!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the subtle changes we made to these Q&amp;amp;As that now adapt based on the plan you select on the previous page. If you&amp;rsquo;re a free user, we address entirely different concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Addressing HookFeed Customer Objections" src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/smallhq/old-vs-new-objections.gif" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Will I be charged [now vs. anything]?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I&amp;rsquo;m signing up to become a free user of a product, and I see &amp;ldquo;Will I be charged now?&amp;rdquo; in the FAQs&amp;hellip;it leads me to believe that at some point in the future, I will be charged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whereas if I&amp;rsquo;m signing up for a paid plan with a trial, my main concern is that I won&amp;rsquo;t be charged until my trial has completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also clarify that if you ever do need to upgrade, we will give you advance notice before making any changes to your account that will trigger a charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Why do you need my card?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to the first question, if our explanation of why we need your credit card includes language about your trial expiring, then it&amp;rsquo;s natural to assume that something will change at that point in time for your account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Free trial?! I thought I was signing up for a free plan!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why we changed the language for free users to not mention a trial in any way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For paid customers, we focus on keeping your account functional rather than emphasizing &amp;ldquo;back-and-forth&amp;rdquo; hassle when your trial ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What Can You Do to Avoid the Same Mistakes?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every new feature or change in direction requires that you revisit old pages, copy, and positioning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no &amp;ldquo;done&amp;rdquo; with SaaS products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you grow, this laundry list of product aspects to monitor and keep up-to-date grows so do your best to limit your early scope to the bare minimum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constantly revisit the flows that your customers experience. When each member of your team goes heads-down on improving parts of your product, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to neglect the experience as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Get Out of Denial About Your Startup's Priorities</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.hookfeed.com/blog/get-out-of-denial-about-your-startups-priorities/"/>
    <id>http://www.hookfeed.com/blog/get-out-of-denial-about-your-startups-priorities/</id>
    <published>2014-04-02T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-04-02T09:20:24-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Matt Goldman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Get Out of Denial About Your Startup’s Priorities" src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/HookFeed/denial_blog_header.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Get Out of Denial About Your Startup’s Priorities&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;With One, Simple Question.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As startup founders, we’re all looking for ways to move that needle. But when was the last time you stopped to question your efforts and whether or not they’re the ‘right ones’? I can say I did this zero times…until a few weeks ago. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recent chat with &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hnshah"&gt;Hiten Shah&lt;/a&gt;, he told me that the thing he sees early startups struggle with the most, time and time again, is misplaced focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t the answer I was expecting. Or maybe I should say, it wasn’t the answer I was hoping for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted a concrete, common reason like, “Most early startups focus too much on customer development, marketing, product features, scaling, etc… when they should be doing [BLANK].” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Misplaced focus,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And he hit the nail on the head. So why was that such an unsatisfying answer? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I wanted that magic bullet! Do x instead of y. Boom. No matter what size, shape, stage, or market — just do x! Instead of being handed a cure-all, &lt;strong&gt;I was forced to face something I’d long been putting off&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding the right focus and the right set of tasks is something I’ve been personally struggling with on &lt;a href="http://www.hookfeed.com?utm_source=hookfeed-blog&amp;amp;utm_medium=blog&amp;amp;utm_campaign=get-out-of-denial"&gt;HookFeed&lt;/a&gt; for the past few months without admitting it. I was guilty. And now I was forced to look at the problem head-on, and figure out what the hell to do about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Denial is a Sneaky Thing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s funny how we are able to slip into denial about all kinds of things in life without even realizing it’s happening. We humans are very good at deceiving ourselves. As &lt;a href="http://www.motherjones.com/politics/2011/03/denial-science-chris-mooney"&gt;Chris Mooney&lt;/a&gt; puts it, &lt;em&gt;“when we think we’re reasoning, we’re often rationalizing.”&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the underlying reason for denial (self-preservation, pride, laziness, fear, etc.) we’re so damn good at it that we usually don’t even realize we’re doing it. We trick ourselves into some false reality without trying to do so. It’s actually amazing! But it’s dangerous. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing about denial is, it never works long-term. Reality bats last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Let me give you an example:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I was busy all day — so I’m making progress towards my goal.”&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know this is bullshit. But I’d be willing to bet you’re guilty of this mentality. We justify this to ourselves all the time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This false reality that busy = productive is dangerous. The &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; reality is that it doesn’t matter how busy you are if you’re not actually accomplishing your goal. If you can reach your goal with almost no effort, great! It really has little to do with how hard you work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putting in more hours is not a badge of honor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, it’s quite the opposite. I’d love be able to put less in and get more out. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are always going to be plenty of outside factors that make it difficult to reach your goals — but do you ever stop to ask yourself if the things within your control, the things you are doing are the right things for that exact point in time? I rarely did… until recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Confession: I don’t know what the hell I’m doing.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re in a phase with &lt;a href="http://www.hookfeed.com?utm_source=hookfeed-blog&amp;amp;utm_medium=blog&amp;amp;utm_campaign=get-out-of-denial"&gt;HookFeed&lt;/a&gt;, that we’ve never been in before. We’re past all the super early half-baked versions. We’ve got a clear roadmap. The product is incredibly valuable (in my humble opinion ☺). It’s time to sell subscriptions. &lt;strong&gt;It’s time to grow!&lt;/strong&gt; And I’m responsible for moving the needle — which is a new, scary frontier for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve written before about how when too many choices are in front of you, analysis paralysis sets in. But, what about when the choices themselves are unclear?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m faced with challenges that are so new I don’t even know where to start. So I don’t. I work on all of the things I know how to do, whether or not they’re the things that will get that needle to move. I do the things I know I’m good at. I stay plenty busy. And the needle doesn’t move. This, my friends, is denial. And it’s a recipe for failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;So How’s That Working for You?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t help but think back to an instructor I once had. Big, booming, Belgian guy with a killer accent. He’d ask this one question that just came back to me as I sit here writing this post. You’d tell him about your struggles in achieving some goal (getting your team to work better together, getting a promotion at work, losing weight… whatever). You’d list off the things you’d been doing to try and achieve it. And after each action you listed, he’d ask:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“And how’s that working for you?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’d list off something else you did and he’d ask again. &lt;em&gt;“And how’s that working for you?”&lt;/em&gt; He did this incessantly… often to the point of berating the person. But his point was clear every time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you keep doing things that aren’t working, you’ll never get there. Try something else. If that doesn’t work, try something else. Get creative. Problem solve. Attack things from different angles. But stop spending your energy doing things you know don’t work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Persistence does not equal progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing about running a startup is that there’s never a clear-cut path. I know we’re going to make lots of mistakes. It’s part of the fun and a component of a unique, lifelong education. In fact, the freedom to make them is part of why I got into this business instead of something easier or more secure. But in order to grow (not just move the needle, but grow personally) I’m going to need to get comfortable being uncomfortable. I’m going to have to experiment, try new things — fail fast and move on. I need to avoid the opportunity for denial and take that instructor’s advice to be more mindful about what I’m doing, and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is why at the end of every day I now spend a few minutes (that’s all it takes) to think about what I did and ask myself &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“how’s this working for me?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How to Boost SaaS Cash Flow by Exploiting December</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.hookfeed.com/blog/how-to-boost-saas-cash-flow-by-exploiting-december/"/>
    <id>http://www.hookfeed.com/blog/how-to-boost-saas-cash-flow-by-exploiting-december/</id>
    <published>2013-12-23T08:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-04-01T12:39:56-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Matt Goldman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Boost December Software as a Service Cash Flow" src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/HookFeed/december-cash-flow%402x.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;How to Boost SaaS Cash Flow by Exploiting December&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;December can be a fickle month for sales in the SaaS biz. But we think we’ve discovered a way to squeeze the most juice out of the lemon and turn December into a powerhouse month for cash flow by taking advantage of one simple reality:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Year-End Budget Surpluses&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I dive into our tactics, let me back up to the origins of this strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Spring, I flew to Vegas for a little SaaS conference. It ended up being my best business decision all year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hesitate to tell you which conference, because I worry that if more people catch on…prices will increase and attendance will become even more limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ah hell, it was &lt;a href="http://www.microconf.com/"&gt;MicroConf&lt;/a&gt; !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within minutes of the first talk by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/asmartbear"&gt;Jason Cohen&lt;/a&gt;, I was writing frantically jotting down notes about what’s worked for his company, &lt;a href="http://wpengine.com/"&gt;WP Engine&lt;/a&gt;. Many of the strategies were simple, and seemed obvious in hindsight, but they had significant impacts on the cash flow of his company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gist was this: by pushing monthly-paying customers towards annual plans, cash flow would increase to the extent that their marketing budget was covered. They were essentially raising investment from their current customers who trusted them most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past few months, we’ve struggled with &lt;a href="http://www.hookfeed.com"&gt;HookFeed&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.minimalytics.com"&gt;Minimalytics&lt;/a&gt; to find opportunities to increase cash flow via an annual plan option. It can be difficult when your product is brand new, or when you know you haven’t found product-market fit quite yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At MicroConf, Jason detailed a few strategies that they use to increase cash flow. One of them really stood out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They send an email a few months after sign up, re-iterating the discount for paying annually. &lt;a href="http://moz.com/rand/"&gt;Rand Fishkin&lt;/a&gt; wrote a bit about this email &lt;a href="http://moz.com/rand/exceptional-upgrade-path-ux-from-wpengine/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jason isn&amp;rsquo;t the only one doing this sort of marketing. Just the other day, I received this email from &lt;a href="https://www.codeship.io/"&gt;CodeShip&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="CodeShip Annual Upgrade Email" src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/HookFeed/codeship-annual-email.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this morning, I received the following well-timed email from &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/brennandunn"&gt;Brennan Dunn&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Quick — what&amp;rsquo;s tax deductible for 2013 and has helped over 5,000 freelancers get more clients and make more money? If you guessed my books, you&amp;rsquo;re right :-) Today, and just today, I&amp;rsquo;m putting both on sale for the next few hours [&amp;hellip;]&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can tell you that as soon as I read these emails, the gears were turning in my head calculating how much I’d save&amp;hellip;thinking it’s a no-brainer to upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we weren’t currently running leaner than normal, we absolutely would have upgraded our CodeShip account. And now that I know it’s an option, I’ll probably upgrade to annual billing in the future once our own SaaS revenues increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you show happy customers pricing options, they no longer need to choose whether or not to buy&amp;hellip;they need to choose how much to pay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these strategies are great — especially when you’re targeting existing customers. But we just launched &lt;a href="http://www.hookfeed.com"&gt;HookFeed&lt;/a&gt; last week. If we’re waiting a few months to send an upgrade promotion email, or triggering it based on heavy usage, people won’t be seeing those promotions for some time. And we’ll have to wait even longer to see a bump in our cash flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we asked ourselves, &amp;ldquo;What can we do upon launch, in a tough month, to entice annual plan signups?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Using Timing to Increase Your SaaS Cash Flow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many businesses, December is a month of blowing budgets. Many companies have budget surpluses heading into the end of the year and are much looser with how they spend funds than they are in surrounding months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, employees are often encouraged to spend any remaining budget they can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know about you, but that sounds like a gold mine to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reached out to some friends to ask about their experience with budget surpluses, and learned a bit about budgets in large companies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;In fact employees are often encouraged to spend any remaining budget they have. In contrast to startups; big business department annual budgets can put departments in a &amp;lsquo;use it or lose it&amp;rsquo; scenario. Where annual budgets may not roll over to the next year.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/kevinsmoker"&gt;Kevin Smoker&lt;/a&gt; - Project Manager at &lt;a href="http://www.lifetechnologies.com/"&gt;Life Technologies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And about the tax benefits of making certain purchases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Businesses are incentived to spend year end budgets because these purchases are at a &amp;lsquo;pre-tax&amp;rsquo; discount of up to 39%.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/michaelsacca"&gt;Michael Sacca&lt;/a&gt; - Co-Founder of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/TinyFactorySD"&gt;Tiny Factory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Implementing Annual Discounts in Our Product&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s how we approached this with &lt;a href="http://www.hookfeed.com"&gt;HookFeed&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We modified our homepage design before launch, in order to push the annual plan harder than previously planned. After a few iterations, we decided the following aspects were important:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Promotion text in the pricing section speaking directly to any visitors who may be looking to spend their remaining budgets&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Make it clear that the promotion is only available through the end of the year — adding some urgency (we’re offering 3 months free versus the regular 2 months free when paying annually).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Decided to still default to monthly prices so as not to give sticker shock to those who want to choose monthly billing&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Added a checkbox saying &amp;ldquo;I want three months free&amp;rdquo; which toggles the price to the annual plan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.hookfeed.com"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is what we ended up with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="HookFeed's Approach to Annual Pricing Discounts #1" src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/HookFeed/hookfeed-annual-pricing-header.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="HookFeed's Approach to Annual Pricing Discounts #2" src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/HookFeed/hookfeed-annual-pricing.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an early-stage, bootstrapped SaaS, cash flow is a top priority. If you’re in a similar boat, it should be your priority as well. It is the one metric that decides whether we’ll still be working on our products in X months and not looking for jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if I can combine a small tweak with good timing to yield a cash-flow surge, you bet your ass I’m gonna try!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
